<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Election Prediction Blog</title>
    <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Election Prediction Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2. The Importance of the Economy</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-14-2-the-importance-of-the-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-14-2-the-importance-of-the-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-the-economy-relate-to-election-outcomes&#34;&gt;How does the economy relate to election outcomes?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many scholars argue that most presidential elections are determined by political and economic conditions called fundamentals, which exist outside of campaign efforts by either party. Factors like economic growth, disposable income, inflation, and the cost of living, which are often economic circumstances of the previous administration, are found to be highly correlated with election outcomes. This phenomenon is known as retrospective economic voting, wherein a voter makes choices based on the incumbent&amp;rsquo;s past performance, with a specific focus on the economy &lt;a href=&#34;https://hollis.harvard.edu/permalink/f/1s5nto6/01HVD_ALMA512397392810003941&#34;&gt;Achen and Bartels, 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1. Exploring Electoral Competitiveness</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-08-1-exploring-electoral-competitiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-08-1-exploring-electoral-competitiveness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-competitive-are-presidential-elections-in-the-united-states&#34;&gt;How competitive are presidential elections in the United States?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to predict the outcome of the 2024 presidential election, it is important to base the prediction model on an understanding of past elections at the national level.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, national elections have been competitive between the two major parties since the election of President Franklin Roosevelt in 1948. In the succeeding 75+ years, neither party has been able to maintain a significant monopoly over the Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Hugo XMin</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;XMin&lt;/strong&gt; is the first Hugo theme I have designed. The original reason that I wrote it was I needed a minimal example of Hugo themes when I was writing the  &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;blogdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; book. Basically I wanted a simple theme that supports a navigation menu, a home page, other single pages, lists of pages, blog posts, categories, tags, and RSS. That is all. Nothing fancy. In terms of CSS and JavaScript, I really want to keep them minimal. In fact, this theme does not contain any JavaScript code at all, although on this example website I did introduce some JavaScript code (still relatively simple anyway). The theme does not contain any images, either, and is pretty much a plain-text theme.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
