<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Election Prediction Blog</title>
    <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Election Prediction Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>8. Final Prediction Post</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-27-8-final-prediction-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-27-8-final-prediction-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-predict-an-election-outcome&#34;&gt;How to predict an election outcome?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over the past seven weeks, I have been working to build a model which can effectively predict the outcome of the 2024 presidential election. Now, with a little over a week until election day, it is time to utilize my knowledge to produce a comprehensive election forecast.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My final model will include five predictive variables —&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q2 GDP Growth&lt;/strong&gt;: In &lt;a href=&#34;(https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-14-2-the-importance-of-the-economy/)&#34;&gt;week two&lt;/a&gt; we began our discussion of fundamentals, covering the effect of the economy on incumbent vote share. Week two&amp;rsquo;s model discovered the significant relationship between Q2 GDP growth and vote share, above all other economic variables.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Latest Poll Averages&lt;/strong&gt;: Polling was covered in &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-18-3-incorporating-polling/&#34;&gt;week three&lt;/a&gt;. The regularized regression model from that post discovered that the weeks with the greatest predictive power were those closest to the election. In this way, the model only includes recent polling data&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incumbency&lt;/strong&gt;: The incumbency advantage was discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-27-4-the-incumbency-advantage/&#34;&gt;week four&lt;/a&gt; wherein we weighed the effects of name recognition, pork-barrel spending, and candidate fatigue. Incumbent status proves to be a major predictor of election outcomes; however, this effect is complicated by the candidate switch from Biden to Harris. Regardless, incumbency proved predictive in my week four model, thus it is incorporated here as well.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Democratic Two-Party Vote Share Lagged One Cycle&lt;/strong&gt;: In &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-02-5-demographics-turnout-and-vote-choice/&#34;&gt;week five&lt;/a&gt;, we covered the effects of out final fundamental variable: demographics. As the electorate becomes further calcified, demographics are increasingly predictive of both turnout and election outcomes. It is difficult, however, to predict demographic shifts on existing data. Indeed, lagged vote share serves as a proxy for this variable (and others) by displaying how the state has voted in past elections.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Democratic Two-Party Vote Share Lagged Two Cycles&lt;/strong&gt;: By including lagged vote share from both the previous cycle and the one before that, the model is able to account for shifts within the state — i.e. demographic, turnout, or campaign strategy changes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Significantly, this model does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; include campaign variables covered in &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-09-6-on-air-the-addition-of-campaign-advertising/&#34;&gt;week 6&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/&#34;&gt;week 7&lt;/a&gt;. There are three primary reasons for this choice: 1. As political scholars point out, the election can often be predicted on fundamentals alone due to a tug-of-war effect wherein each candidate, campaigning at a similar volume, cancels out the effect of their opponent&amp;rsquo;s campaign. 2. Due to the ever-changing and increasingly dynamic nature of campaigning, there is little historical data to incorporate into the model. Limited data will often generate model bias, which would inhibit my understanding of the predictive power of the variables listed above. 3. Over the past month, Kamala Harris raised over 1 billion dollars in donations &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/livecoverage/harris-trump-election-10-21-2024/card/contributions-to-kamala-harris-topped-1-billion-in-third-quarter-C1LmXXd819zmR3vzZAWX&#34;&gt;(Wall Street Journal, 2024)&lt;/a&gt;. Indeed, campaign spending and mobilization has become unprecedented, calling into question the predictive power of campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7. The Ground Game</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/index_files/kePrint/kePrint.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;link href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/index_files/lightable/lightable.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;&#xA;&lt;script src=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/index_files/kePrint/kePrint.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;link href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/index_files/lightable/lightable.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;&#xA;&lt;script src=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/index_files/kePrint/kePrint.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;link href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/index_files/lightable/lightable.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;&#xA;&lt;script src=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/index_files/kePrint/kePrint.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;link href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-16-7-the-ground-game/index_files/lightable/lightable.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-role-does-the-campaign-play-in-determining-election-outcomes&#34;&gt;What role does the campaign play in determining election outcomes?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presidential campaigns have three main purposes — to convince donors, persuade voters, and mobilize the electorate.&lt;/strong&gt; Last weeks blog discussed one of the mechanisms by which campaigns seek to attain this goal: the air war of mass media campaign advertising. This week&amp;rsquo;s post will explore the ground game, through which campaigns attempt to target individual voters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6. On Air: The Addition of Campaign Advertising</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-09-6-on-air-the-addition-of-campaign-advertising/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-09-6-on-air-the-addition-of-campaign-advertising/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-role-does-the-campaign-play-in-determining-election-outcomes&#34;&gt;What role does the campaign play in determining election outcomes?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Throughout the past five weeks, my blog has focused on exploring fundamentals like &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-14-2-the-importance-of-the-economy/&#34;&gt;the economy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-18-3-incorporating-polling/&#34;&gt;polling&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-27-4-the-incumbency-advantage/&#34;&gt;incumbency&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-02-5-demographics-turnout-and-vote-choice/&#34;&gt;demographics&lt;/a&gt;. These discussions may generate a false understanding that elections are pre-determined, as they are predictable on a small set of fundamental variables. In reality, fundamentals only represent a partial understanding of the temperature of the American electorate. &lt;strong&gt;To truly predict the outcome of presidential elections, it is also important to take into account the 6.6 billion dollar presidential campaign industry.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5. Demographics, Turnout, and Vote Choice</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-02-5-demographics-turnout-and-vote-choice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-10-02-5-demographics-turnout-and-vote-choice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-connections-if-any-between-demographics-and-voter-turnout&#34;&gt;What are the connections, if any, between demographics and voter turnout?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When visiting our class a month ago, FiveThirtyEight&amp;rsquo;s Elliott Morris was asked what variable he wishes he had complete access to for the sake of improving the predictive power of his forecasting models. His answer: voter turnout.&lt;/strong&gt; While forecasters may be able to develop models which accurately gauge the sentiment of the electorate, without information on voter turnout there is no way to accurately extrapolate such &amp;ldquo;temperature checks&amp;rdquo; into accurate election predictions. Yet, pollsters struggle to accurately gauge voter turnout with survey data. Indeed, forecasters often turn to demographics, hoping to impute turnout based on the likelihood of certain populations to turn out to vote. &lt;em&gt;To do so, an assumption must be made that demographic information is able to predict voter turnout. This assumption will be explored below:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4. The Incumbency Advantage</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-27-4-the-incumbency-advantage/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-27-4-the-incumbency-advantage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-advantage-of-incumbency-in-presidential-elections&#34;&gt;What is the advantage of incumbency in presidential elections?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There have been 18 presidential elections since World War II, eleven of which featured an incumbent president running, seven of whom won re-election.&lt;/strong&gt; Indeed, while an incumbent president has won re-election in 33% of elections since WWII, the incumbent party has won over 44% of such presidential elections. These results highlight a key reality in U.S. politics: incumbency is a major advantage for both politicians and parties in the context of a presidential election.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3. Incorporating Polling</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-18-3-incorporating-polling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-18-3-incorporating-polling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-we-best-use-polls-to-predict-election-outcomes&#34;&gt;How can we best use polls to predict election outcomes?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Polls are central to understanding democratic discourse as they measure the average person&amp;rsquo;s opinion. Since January 1, 2024 there have been &lt;strong&gt;13,626 large-scale presidential polls&lt;/strong&gt; conducted to gauge sentiment towards the general election candidates. From 1968 to 2020, &lt;em&gt;general election polling has largely been an accurate predictor of election outcomes&lt;/em&gt;, with an average polling miss of 1.58 percentage points in terms of popular vote. Much of this accuracy stems from a concept which dates back to Galton&amp;rsquo;s Ox, wherein a large sample of guesses — or, in this case, opinions — will generate an average that accurately approximates the general opinion due to the cancellation of error in both directions. &lt;a href=&#34;https://hollis.harvard.edu/permalink/f/1mdq5o5/TN_cdi_crossref_primary_10_1038_075450a0&#34;&gt;(Galton, 1907)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2. The Importance of the Economy</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-14-2-the-importance-of-the-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-14-2-the-importance-of-the-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-the-economy-relate-to-election-outcomes&#34;&gt;How does the economy relate to election outcomes?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many scholars argue that most presidential elections are determined by political and economic conditions called fundamentals, which exist outside of campaign efforts by either party. Factors like &lt;em&gt;economic growth&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;disposable income&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;inflation&lt;/em&gt;, and the &lt;em&gt;cost of living&lt;/em&gt;, which are often economic circumstances of the previous administration, are found to be highly correlated with election outcomes. This phenomenon is known as &lt;strong&gt;retrospective economic voting&lt;/strong&gt;, wherein a voter makes choices based on the incumbent&amp;rsquo;s past performance, with a specific focus on the economy &lt;a href=&#34;https://hollis.harvard.edu/permalink/f/1s5nto6/01HVD_ALMA512397392810003941&#34;&gt;(Achen and Bartels, 2017)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1. Exploring Electoral Competitiveness</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-08-1-exploring-electoral-competitiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-08-1-exploring-electoral-competitiveness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-competitive-are-presidential-elections-in-the-united-states&#34;&gt;How competitive are presidential elections in the United States?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to predict the outcome of the 2024 presidential election, it is important to base the prediction model on an understanding of past elections at the national level.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, national elections have been competitive between the two major parties since the election of President Franklin Roosevelt in 1948. In the succeeding 75+ years, neither party has been able to maintain a significant monopoly over the Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Hugo XMin</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;XMin&lt;/strong&gt; is the first Hugo theme I have designed. The original reason that I wrote it was I needed a minimal example of Hugo themes when I was writing the  &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;blogdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; book. Basically I wanted a simple theme that supports a navigation menu, a home page, other single pages, lists of pages, blog posts, categories, tags, and RSS. That is all. Nothing fancy. In terms of CSS and JavaScript, I really want to keep them minimal. In fact, this theme does not contain any JavaScript code at all, although on this example website I did introduce some JavaScript code (still relatively simple anyway). The theme does not contain any images, either, and is pretty much a plain-text theme.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
