<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Election Prediction Blog</title>
    <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Election Prediction Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>3. Incorporating Polling</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-18-3-incorporating-polling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-18-3-incorporating-polling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-we-best-use-polls-to-predict-election-outcomes&#34;&gt;How can we best use polls to predict election outcomes?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Polls are central to understanding democratic discourse as they measure the average person&amp;rsquo;s opinion. Since January 1, 2024 there have been &lt;strong&gt;13,626 large-scale presidential polls&lt;/strong&gt; conducted to gauge sentiment towards the general election candidates. From 1968 to 2020, &lt;em&gt;general election polling has largely been an accurate predictor of election outcomes&lt;/em&gt;, with an average polling miss of 1.58 percentage points in terms of popular vote. Much of this accuracy stems from a concept which dates back to Galton&amp;rsquo;s Ox, wherein a large sample of guesses — or, in this case, opinions — will generate an average that approximates the general population&amp;rsquo;s opinion as error in both ways cancels out. &lt;a href=&#34;https://hollis.harvard.edu/permalink/f/1mdq5o5/TN_cdi_crossref_primary_10_1038_075450a0&#34;&gt;(Galton, 1907)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2. The Importance of the Economy</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-14-2-the-importance-of-the-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-14-2-the-importance-of-the-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-the-economy-relate-to-election-outcomes&#34;&gt;How does the economy relate to election outcomes?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many scholars argue that most presidential elections are determined by political and economic conditions called fundamentals, which exist outside of campaign efforts by either party. Factors like &lt;em&gt;economic growth&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;disposable income&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;inflation&lt;/em&gt;, and the &lt;em&gt;cost of living&lt;/em&gt;, which are often economic circumstances of the previous administration, are found to be highly correlated with election outcomes. This phenomenon is known as &lt;strong&gt;retrospective economic voting&lt;/strong&gt;, wherein a voter makes choices based on the incumbent&amp;rsquo;s past performance, with a specific focus on the economy &lt;a href=&#34;https://hollis.harvard.edu/permalink/f/1s5nto6/01HVD_ALMA512397392810003941&#34;&gt;(Achen and Bartels, 2017)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1. Exploring Electoral Competitiveness</title>
      <link>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-08-1-exploring-electoral-competitiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://menemshasolomon.github.io/election-blog/post/2024-09-08-1-exploring-electoral-competitiveness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-competitive-are-presidential-elections-in-the-united-states&#34;&gt;How competitive are presidential elections in the United States?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to predict the outcome of the 2024 presidential election, it is important to base the prediction model on an understanding of past elections at the national level.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, national elections have been competitive between the two major parties since the election of President Franklin Roosevelt in 1948. In the succeeding 75+ years, neither party has been able to maintain a significant monopoly over the Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
